Every day at work and at home we need to have difficult conversations so I want to
share with you a very quick, very effective, four-step model that can help you
to do this. It's called the room model. Recognize, use, understand and manage and
this is all to do with emotions. So, recognize how am I feeling and how might the
other person be feeling? The second is use. Use is about assessing what is the
impact of emotions on thoughts and behavior. So, for example, you might note in
yourself that you are feeling resentful and defensive and that is leading you
in your behavior to shut down and close off. Now, understand is about thinking
about what is the cause of this emotion and also how do I want the emotion to
play out over time. In other words, how do I at the end of the conversation want
to be feeling and how do I want the other person to be feeling? And then lastly
is manage. Manage is about thinking what do you need to do in the conversation to
get the emotional outcome that you need? Is it about creating space for
conversation? Is it about listening and being quiet? What is it that is needed in
order to get the outcome? This set of skills, this room model, I think, is
foundational to effective conversations. Too often we go into conversations
thinking about what I want to say in a way that feels really hooked on the
difficulty motion or that's focused on facts and techniques. But what makes
funny effect of conversation is how we manage the emotional tone of the
conversation, both in ourselves and in the other person.